<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on Statistical and Theoretical Ecology Group</title>
    <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/pages/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Statistical and Theoretical Ecology Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://statntheorecol.github.io/pages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ANTOPTIC</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/antoptic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/antoptic/</guid>
      <description>Xysticus sp. preying on Lobesia botrana in the field
© copyright : Sylvie Richart Cervera [INRAE]  
The ANTOPTIC (Analysis of trophic network to optimize the delivery of natural pest control services) project, led by SAVE and BioGeCo (INRA), aims to answer main two questions:
1) What are the effects of farming practices and landscape context on the structure of arthropod food webs in vineyards?
2) What is the relationship between the structure of arthopod food webs and the levels of pest control ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Christelle Aluome</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/christelle-aluome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/christelle-aluome/</guid>
      <description>I am a bio-informatics engineer with a particular expertise in data mining and database development.
Generally speaking, I am interested in everything linked with data mining: management, exploitation and analysis (especially for big volumes of data). I used to work in vegetable genomics, in diverse projects related to data mining, which includes database design (associated with the development of a website), analysis of sequences from NGS techniques (Populus nigra, Pisum sativum), the development of procedure for genome reconstruction (de novo assembly) in the case of small computing resources, and the development of protocols for the selection of SNP which can be applied to genotyping chip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frédéric Barraquand</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/frederic-barraquand/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/frederic-barraquand/</guid>
      <description>I am a quantitative ecologist, with interests ranging from population dynamics or coexistence theory to the statistical analysis of time series.
Much of my research deals with ecological interactions in a dynamic setting (and sometimes a spatially explicit one).
Current projects include, on the technical side:
 multivariate time series methods to infer causal relationships data fusion techniques for mechanistic ecological models identifiability properties of such models individual-based modelling using point processes  Some fundamental ecological questions that interest me:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Members</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/</guid>
      <description>Current Frédéric Barraquand | Researcher Matthieu Paquet | Postdoc Interns  Mélanie Bertrand Impact of urban and periurban environments on butterfly communities (M2) Thomas Besognet Inferring predator-prey interactions through time series models (M1)  Past Coralie Picoche | PhD student 2019-2022 Eivind Kleiven | PhD student 2018-2022 Supervised jointly w/ R.A. Ims, N.G. Yoccoz, E. Soininen at the University of Tromsø
Alix Sauve | Post-doc 2016 - 2019 Interns  Guillaume Doyen Supersaturated coexistence in community dynamics models (L3 2022 with FB) Tewann Beauchard Integrated population models identifiability (M2 2022 with FB &amp;amp; MP) Juliette Conquet Urban pollinators in Bordeaux and survey protocol development (L3 2022 with FB &amp;amp; F Revers Biogeco) Valentine Laurent Responses of Odonata to urban pressures (M1 2021 with FB) &amp;ndash; now studying in Göttingen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Themes</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description>Ecology Our research topics range from behavioural to community ecology. We often keep a strong focus on the population level. Some core questions of interest are
 What are the drivers of population cycles (regular oscillations in population size with &amp;gt;2 orders of magnitude)?
 To what extent do predators regulate their prey?
 How can seemingly similar species manage to coexist?
  These questions can involve either general theoretical modelling or statistical modelling based on long-term data for a given population/community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oops</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 10:53:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/blog/</guid>
      <description>Sorry, blog is not available yet. The lab-elf is working on it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 10:53:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description> A couple of projects involving multiple team members:
Phytoplankton dynamics Biodiver&amp;rsquo;Cité ANTOPTIC </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 10:53:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/publications/</guid>
      <description>Preprints and submitted papers Paquet M., Barraquand F. Assessing species interactions using integrated predator-prey models
Picoche C., Young W.R. &amp;amp; Barraquand F. Local intraspecific aggregation in phytoplankton model communities: spatial scales of occurrence and implications for coexistence
Doyen G., Picoche C. &amp;amp; Barraquand F. [Re] Biodiversity of plankton by species oscillations and chaos (Submitted to ReScience)
Barraquand F. No sensitivity to functional forms in the strongly forced, continuous-time stochastic Rosenzweig-MacArthur model (under review)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BiodiverCité</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/biodivercite/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 06:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/biodivercite/</guid>
      <description>The ‘Biodiver&amp;rsquo;Cité’ project aims at designing guidelines for the preservation of biodiversity in urban landscapes.
The first version of this project (2017-2020) had four major objectives :
1) quantify biodiversity in the urban and suburban landscapes of the city of Bordeaux. This is done in a multi-taxa framework, using major groups of terrestrial and aquatic fauna, based on historical databases as well as new data collection (groups targeted include butterflies, damselflies, dragonflies, amphibians, fishes)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EPIZHONE</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/epizhone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/epizhone/</guid>
      <description>Study zone (Water Streams © BD Cartage ; Wetlands © Adour-Garonne Water Agency ; Superficial water masses © SDAGE) 
In collaboration with Gretha, EPOC and IRSTEA research teams, we aim to characterize the wetland biodiversity of the area of Les Jalles-Blanquefort on the Gironde estuary. We partner with local observatories regarding biological data sets, in an attempt to gather information on both flora and fauna in the area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phytoplankton dynamics</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/phytoplankton-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/projects/phytoplankton-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Time series analysis In collaboration with Ifremer Arcachon, we work on phytoplankton community dynamics, especially diatoms (one of the most abundant classes of plankton, actively involved in biogeochemical cycles).
We are particularly interested in:
 Drivers of blooms Coexistence mechanisms  Our research combines long-term data with statistical and theoretical models.
Our analyses of the time series in Arcachon Bay can be found in Barraquand et al. 2018, Oikos. This work has been extended to the French coastline in Picoche et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coralie Picoche</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/coralie-picoche/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/coralie-picoche/</guid>
      <description>I am currently a PhD student at the Institute of Mathematics of Bordeaux, working on fine-scale modelling of phytoplanktonic community dynamics. Brief CV : 2015-2019: Research assistant, in quantitative ecology at the University of Bordeaux, Integrative and Theoretical Ecology group (France)
2014 : Research assistant in fishery modelling, at the Institute of Research for Development, Exploited Marine Ecosystems Department (South Africa)
2012-2013 : Research assistant in shellfish modelling, at the French Research Institute for Exploitation of the Sea (France).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yohan Sahraoui</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/past-members/yohan-sahraoui/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/past-members/yohan-sahraoui/</guid>
      <description>Yohan is now lecturer at UMR THEMA, at the University of Franche-Comté.
Link to his new page(s)  -- 
Publications:
Sahraoui Y., De Godoy Leski C., Benot M-L, Revers F., Salles D., van Halder I., Barneix M., Carassou L. Integrating ecological networks modelling in a participatory approach for assessing impacts of planning scenarios on landscape connectivity. Landscape and Urban Planning, 2021, 209, 104039.
Foltête J-C., Savary P., Clauzel C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alix Sauve</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/past-members/alix-sauve/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/past-members/alix-sauve/</guid>
      <description>I now work as a project officer for the French Comittee of the IUCN, in charge of the Red List of Ecosystems As a community ecologist, I am keen on investigating the structure of ecological communities as well as their dynamics, so as to understand how they respond to disturbances. I study ecological communities as networks of interactions, trying to capture the architecture of such webs, their variabilities and their dynamics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laure Carassou</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/laure-carassou/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/laure-carassou/</guid>
      <description>My main research interest is aquatic ecology, mainly fish assemblage dynamics. I have been studying fish in a variety of ecosystems (estuaries, coral reefs or other coastal and pelagic marine environments from Europe, south Pacific, northern Gulf of Mexico, west and south Africa, northwest Indian Ocean). I combine diverse methodological approaches to provide a comprehensive understanding of the dynamics of fish populations in the context of climatic and environmental variability (trophic studies based on gut contents, stable isotopes, fatty acids, and/or multivariate statistical approaches).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eivind F. Kleiven</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/eivind-kleiven/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/eivind-kleiven/</guid>
      <description>I am interested in population dynamics and interspecific interactions. As wildlife populations and ecological interactions are most often imperfectly observed, I often investigate those topics using statistical models accounting for such imperfect detection. Furthermore, I have a special interest for the tundra food web, where the drivers of ecosystem dynamics are still poorly understood.

My PhD work was part of the long-term monitoring program Climate-ecological Observatory for Arctic Tundra (COAT) and has a focus on rodent population cycles and monitoring of small mammals with camera traps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matthieu Paquet</title>
      <link>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/matthieu-paquet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statntheorecol.github.io/members/matthieu-paquet/</guid>
      <description>I am interested in behavioral ecology and population dynamics. I aim to better understand and predict population fluctuations by integrating information on interactions within (e.g. parental effects and social behaviour) as well as among species (e.g. competition and predation), notably using data integration (Integrated Population and Community Models).

I currently work with Frederic Barraquand on the identifiability of dynamic models including interactions within and between species (Integrated Community Models).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>