<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on Integrative and Theoretical Ecology Group</title>
    <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/pages/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Integrative and Theoretical Ecology Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://itecologyresearch.github.io/pages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ANTOPTIC</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/antoptic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/antoptic/</guid>
      <description>Xysticus sp. preying on Lobesia botrana in the field
© copyright : Sylvie Richart Cervera [INRAE]  
The ANTOPTIC (Analysis of trophic network to optimize the delivery of natural pest control services) project, led by SAVE and BioGeCo (INRA), aims to answer main two questions:
1) What are the effects of farming practices and landscape context on the structure of arthropod food webs in vineyards?
2) What is the relationship between the structure of arthopod food webs and the levels of pest control ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Christelle Aluome</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/christelle-aluome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/christelle-aluome/</guid>
      <description>I am a bio-informatics engineer with a particular expertise in data mining and database development.
Generally speaking, I am interested in everything linked with data mining: management, exploitation and analysis (especially for big volumes of data). I used to work in vegetable genomics, in diverse projects related to data mining, which includes database design (associated with the development of a website), analysis of sequences from NGS techniques (Populus nigra, Pisum sativum), the development of procedure for genome reconstruction (de novo assembly) in the case of small computing resources, and the development of protocols for the selection of SNP which can be applied to genotyping chip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frédéric Barraquand</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/frederic-barraquand/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/frederic-barraquand/</guid>
      <description>I am a quantitative ecologist, with interests ranging from population dynamics or coexistence theory to the statistical analysis of time series.
Most of my research deals with ecological interactions in a dynamic setting (and sometimes a spatially explicit one). Some more details in my personal webpage.
Current projects include, on the technical side:
 multivariate time series methods to infer causal relationships data fusion techniques for mechanistic ecological models identifiability properties of such models  Some fundamental ecological questions that interest me:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Members</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/</guid>
      <description>Current members Christelle Aluome | Research assistant Frédéric Barraquand | Researcher Laure Carassou | Researcher Coralie Picoche | PhD student Past members Yohan Sahraoui | Post-doc 2016 - 2019 Alix Sauve | Post-doc 2016 - 2019 Interns  Valentine Laurent (M1 2021 with FB) &amp;ndash; now studying in Göttingen. Gaël Bardon (M2 2020 with FB) &amp;ndash; now starting a PhD on penguin demographic modelling (Centre Scientifique de Monaco). Sam Boireaud (M2 2019 with FB) Bachar Tarraf (M2 2018 with FB) &amp;ndash; now PhD student at IMB (Institute of Mathematics of Bordeaux), working on biomedical mathematical modelling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Themes</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 10:04:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description>Ecological interactions and dynamics of ecosystems
Species interactions, such as predation, competition or mutualism, play a fundamental role in the structuring and dynamics of animal and plant communities. They can strongly affect fluctuations in population size, species relative abundance and ecosystem functioning. Key ecological phenomena, such as pest outbreaks, biodiversity maintenance, trophic cascades are thought to be directly related to ecological interactions. One of our objectives is to measure and predict the effect of those interactions on the dynamics of co-occurring species.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oops</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 10:53:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/blog/</guid>
      <description>Sorry, blog is not available yet. The lab-elf is working on it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 10:53:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description> Phytoplankton dynamics Biodiver&amp;rsquo;Cité ANTOPTIC </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 10:53:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/publications/</guid>
      <description>Preprints and submitted papers Picoche C., Young W.R., Barraquand F. [Re] Reproductive pair correlations and the clustering of organisms (under review)
Kleiven E.F., Barraquand F., Gimenez O., Henden J-A, Ims R.A., Soininen E.M., Yoccoz N.G. A dynamic occupancy model for interacting species with two spatial scales. (under review)
Bardon G., Barraquand F. Effects of stage structure on coexistence: mixed benefits. (in prep.)
Archambeau J., Benito Garzón M., de Miguel Vega M.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What we do</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 10:53:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/home/</guid>
      <description>Our group focuses on population, community and landscape ecology (sometimes blended with other disciplines). We use modelling tools&amp;ndash;both statistics and theoretical models&amp;ndash;to study a broad range of ecosystems, aquatic and terrestrial. Most of us are/were affiliated with the University of Bordeaux&amp;ndash;previously within the frame of the Labex COTE. The ITE group is co-headed by Laure Carassou (INRAE) and Frederic Barraquand (CNRS).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BiodiverCité</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/biodivercite/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 06:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/biodivercite/</guid>
      <description>The ‘Biodiver&amp;rsquo;Cité’ project aims at designing guidelines for the preservation of biodiversity in urban landscapes.
The first version of this project (2017-2020) had four major objectives :
1) quantify biodiversity in the urban and suburban landscapes of the city of Bordeaux. This is done in a multi-taxa framework, using major groups of terrestrial and aquatic fauna, based on historical databases as well as new data collection (groups targeted include butterflies, damselflies, dragonflies, amphibians, fishes)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EPIZHONE</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/epizhone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/epizhone/</guid>
      <description>Study zone (Water Streams © BD Cartage ; Wetlands © Adour-Garonne Water Agency ; Superficial water masses © SDAGE) 
In collaboration with Gretha, EPOC and IRSTEA research teams, we aim to characterize the wetland biodiversity of the area of Les Jalles-Blanquefort on the Gironde estuary. We partner with local observatories regarding biological data sets, in an attempt to gather information on both flora and fauna in the area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phytoplankton dynamics</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/phytoplankton-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/projects/phytoplankton-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Time series analysis In collaboration with Ifremer Arcachon, we work on phytoplankton community dynamics, especially diatoms (one of the most abundant classes of plankton, actively involved in biogeochemical cycles).
We are particularly interested in:
 Drivers of blooms Coexistence mechanisms  Our research combines long-term data with statistical and theoretical models.
Our analyses of the time series in Arcachon Bay can be found in Barraquand et al. 2018, Oikos. This work has been extended to the French coastline in Picoche et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coralie Picoche</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/coralie-picoche/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/coralie-picoche/</guid>
      <description>I am currently a PhD student at the Institute of Mathematics of Bordeaux, working on fine-scale modelling of phytoplanktonic community dynamics. Brief CV : 2015-2019: Research assistant, in quantitative ecology at the University of Bordeaux, Integrative and Theoretical Ecology group (France)
2014 : Research assistant in fishery modelling, at the Institute of Research for Development, Exploited Marine Ecosystems Department (South Africa)
2012-2013 : Research assistant in shellfish modelling, at the French Research Institute for Exploitation of the Sea (France).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yohan Sahraoui</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/past-members/yohan-sahraoui/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/past-members/yohan-sahraoui/</guid>
      <description>Yohan is now lecturer at UMR THEMA, at the University of Franche-Comté.
Link to his new page(s)  -- 
Publications:
Sahraoui Y., De Godoy Leski C., Benot M-L, Revers F., Salles D., van Halder I., Barneix M., Carassou L. Integrating ecological networks modelling in a participatory approach for assessing impacts of planning scenarios on landscape connectivity. Landscape and Urban Planning, 2021, 209, 104039.
Foltête J-C., Savary P., Clauzel C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alix Sauve</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/past-members/alix-sauve/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/past-members/alix-sauve/</guid>
      <description>I now work as a project officer for the French Comittee of the IUCN, in charge of the Red List of Ecosystems As a community ecologist, I am keen on investigating the structure of ecological communities as well as their dynamics, so as to understand how they respond to disturbances. I study ecological communities as networks of interactions, trying to capture the architecture of such webs, their variabilities and their dynamics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laure Carassou</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/laure-carassou/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 11:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/members/laure-carassou/</guid>
      <description>My main research interest is aquatic ecology, mainly fish assemblage dynamics. I have been studying fish in a variety of ecosystems (estuaries, coral reefs or other coastal and pelagic marine environments from Europe, south Pacific, northern Gulf of Mexico, west and south Africa, northwest Indian Ocean). I combine diverse methodological approaches to provide a comprehensive understanding of the dynamics of fish populations in the context of climatic and environmental variability (trophic studies based on gut contents, stable isotopes, fatty acids, and/or multivariate statistical approaches).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>