<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Integrative and Theoretical Ecology Group</title>
    <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Integrative and Theoretical Ecology Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Under progress...</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 16:30:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://itecologyresearch.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/posts/join-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 16:30:25 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/posts/join-us/</guid>
      <description>We host internships for MSc. students (one per year so far) - contact us if interested to work with us, here are our research themes.
Every year, Bordeaux&amp;rsquo;s Idex has a call for postdoctorate fellowships, these will allow to develop your own research project in collaboration with the group. There is also a visiting scholars programme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back from SFEcologie 2018</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/posts/back-from-sfecologie-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 09:45:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/posts/back-from-sfecologie-2018/</guid>
      <description>We just came back from SFEcologie 2018 &amp;ndash; a great conference in Rennes!
Alix presented her latest work on seasonal dynamic food webs; Coralie had a poster on diversity maintenance in (also seasonal) theoretical competitive communities, and myself a presentation of our empirical analyses of phytoplankton community dynamics.
I really enjoyed Teja Tscharnkte&amp;rsquo;s plenary on integrating biodiversity services in agriculture.
 Teja Tscharntke explains why pollinator diversity is crucial to pollination at #sfe2018 pic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring 2018 news</title>
      <link>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/posts/spring-2018-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 16:39:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://itecologyresearch.github.io/posts/spring-2018-news/</guid>
      <description>Some highlights from the last few months:
April
 Alix and Frederic were in Clermont-Ferrand at Irstea April 10-12 for the Temporal Network working group meeting of the GDR TheoMoDive. We enjoyed good team spirit and discovered a nice new brew (thanks Franck Jabot for organizing!).
 Frederic gave a presentation in the Biostatistics seminar at ISPED / Bordeaux Population Health centre on the 23rd: “Inferring interactions between species using time series of population counts and multivariate autoregressive models”.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>